right there I've noticed that when I
concentrate on something for an extended
period it brings about a sense of bliss
and peace
these states stick around and help me
deal with life's challenges
I wonder if continuing this
concentration practice might lead me to
a point where I become untroubled by
external things but
is this the right path and how long
might it take I've invested a fair bit
of time and I want to make sure that
it's worth life
I would probably need a bit more details
but it doesn't sound like like the right
path because if concentration helps you deal
because if concentration helps you deal
with the life challenges
sounds more like management practice to
me
instead you should ask yourself why are
you challenged in the first place
why do you need concentration to help
you deal with the challenges if you were
no challenge to begin with
you don't need to deal with it you don't
need to concentrate you don't need to do
anything you are unmoved to begin with
that's the direction of practice
if concentration helps you cope
because you just can't bear it fine but
don't confuse that for the practice of
the Dharma because it isn't you wonder
it will not arise it will not result in
understanding because you're you're going the wrong
because you're you're going the wrong
way about it you're going trying to
manage the suffering which is kind of
what pathogenists do because they don't
know the Escape
so for as long as you don't abandon the
value of suffering management
you will not look for the way of
uprooting it you need to basically leave
yourself No Way Out
in order to to seek the true escape from
it
you see the real cold yeah to to
basically if you leave if you stop
managing your suffering if you recognize
that you're surrounded by it like the
king surrounded by the armies from the
four directions
you need then you realize okay the the
weight of the problem and then you can
be able to look for it for way
outrightly through approaching the
craving and that's exemplified with I just said
and that's exemplified with I just said
you ask yourself why am I bothered in
the first place why is life challenging
me why can life challenge me in the
first place rather than oh I found
something that helps me always deal with
different challenges no I want to be not
challenged in the to begin with that's deliberation
that's deliberation
why why am I challenged why am I
challenging to begin with yeah
so the dhamma does not provide
instruction how to deal with the life
challenges the dhamma approves the life
so there are no challenges for you
so you already
well I guess what I got from this
question was like if you if he keeps on
concentrating and focusing
to build up to build up build up these
whole waking moments we'll just culminate on
waking moments we'll just culminate on
its own yeah yeah well that's uh that's
not how it works which is exactly why I
started describing this as two opposite
directions you cannot be managing your
suffering and at the same time trying to uproot it
and at the same time trying to uproot it
because in order to uproot it you need
to stop giving in to the tendency and
craving for management management is a
quick fix
management is depressuring of the
container
and uprooting can occur if the container
is pressure pressurized rightly to the
right extent let's put it that way so
each time you give in to a management
you release the pressure
so it's mutually exclusive
releasing the pressure building
releasing the pressure build in the
pressure
so you have to give up that tendency
towards management
in order for that pressure that's been
built up to turn you in the right
direction see the cause for the for the liability
see the cause for the for the liability
to be bothered
which is uh unwholesome Behavior but
body speech in mind that's still
perpetuated lack of establishment of
virtue lack of sense restraint lack of
knowledge and transparency in regard to
your intentions lack of enduring the
hindrances on the right level without
acting out of them without trying to get
lack of development
then concentration basically provides
you this like a narrow focusing thinning
out where you stop seeing the problems
while it's still very much in front of
your face